<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Chef, | codemachine]]></title>
  <link href="http://ivanbrennan.github.io/blog/categories/chef/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ivanbrennan.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-05T19:58:14-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ivanbrennan.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ivan Brennan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chef roles]]></title>
    <link href="http://ivanbrennan.github.io/blog/2013/11/21/chef-roles/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-21T09:11:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ivanbrennan.github.io/blog/2013/11/21/chef-roles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It took me a while to wrap my head around a Chef role. It sounds simple enough at first &mdash; a collection of recipes that allows a node to act in a certain capacity, as say, a Redis server &mdash; but Chef also deals in cookbooks, which are also collections of recipes. So then what&rsquo;s the difference between a cookbook and a role?</p>

<p>A cookbook is a collection of recipes relating to a particular piece of technology. The nginx cookbook, for example, contains several recipes related to building and configuring nginx: <code>nginx::source</code> builds nginx from source, <code>nginx::ohai_plugin</code> provides the Ohai plugin as a template, <code>nginx::passenger</code> builds the passenger gem, etc.</p>

<p>A node is a single server, and Chef can apply a variety of recipes to the node to set it up as needed. Those recipes can be selected from a variety of cookbooks, and we don&rsquo;t have to use every recipe in a given cookbook. So how do we package the particular mix of recipes we need for a certain type of node? In a role.</p>

<p>For lack of a better analogy, you could think of a role as a multi-course meal made from several recipes pulled from a variety of cookbooks. A couple from a Pasta cookbook, one from a French Cuisine cookbook, one from a Pastries cookbook. The meal won&rsquo;t be made from every single recipe in those books, just the desired ones.</p>

<p>Recipes can include each other too, like mixins in Ruby (the <code>nginx::source</code> recipe, for example, includes the <code>nginx::ohai_plugin</code> recipe as part of it) but let&rsquo;s not add to the confusion just yet.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
